Guide to the Axel Leijonhufvud Papers, 1953-2023 RL.00804
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Axel Leijonhufvud papers
1953-2023
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Leijonhufvud, Axel
RL.00804
7.5 Linear Feet 13 boxes.
Axel Leijonhufvud (1933-2022) was a professor emeritus of economics at the University of California, Los Angeles. This collection documents his professional life through his correspondence, writings, and research. Acquired as part of the Economists' Papers Archive.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Biographical Information; Correspondence; and Research, Writing, and Works.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Axel Leijonhufvud papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library as a gift in 1997 and as a gift from Earlene Craver Leijonhufvud in 2023.
Biographical / Historical
Chronology List
1933 Born in Stockholm, Sweden
1960 BA, University of Lund
1961 MA, University of Pittsburgh
1964 Acting Assistant Professor, University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA)
1967 PhD, Economics, Northwestern University
1967 Assistant Professor, UCLA
1968 On Keynesian Economics and the Economics of Keynes: A Study in Monetary Theory
1971-1994 Professor, UCLA
1991-1997 Founder and Director of Center for Computable Economics, UCLA
1995-2008 Professor of Monetary Theory and Policy, University of Trento
2000 Macroeconomic Instability and Coordination: Selected Essays
2007-2011 Wrote over a dozen articles for Council of Economic Policy Research (CEPR) and VoxEU on fiscal crises of European Union
2022 May 02 Died in Los Angeles, CA
Related Materials
Robert W. Clower papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Scope and Contents
This collections consists of Leijonhufvud's correspondence, writings, research, and teaching material from his career as a Keynesian economist and professor. Contents range from his coursework at the University of Pittsburgh to lecture notes from his early years as a professor at the University of California, Los Angeles. Topics include include macroeconomic theory, instability and (dis)equilibrium economics, monetary theory and policies, inflation, banking, market systems, Keynesian thought, and the history of economics in general. Correspondents include Armen Alchian, Robert W. Clower (coauthor), Robert Dorfman, Alan G. Gowman, Bert Hoselitz, Erik Lundberg, Gunnar Myrdal, and Joan Robinson.
Banks and banking; Economists -- United States -- Correspondence; Equilibrium (Economics); Inflation (Finance); Keynesian economics; Macroeconomics and finance; Monetary policy; Clower, Robert W.; Economists' Papers Archive; Leijonhufvud, Axel; Lundberg, Erik, 1895-1969; University of California, Los Angeles. Department of Economics -- Faculty
- Biographical Information, 2022-2023
  - Lecture photograph, 2023 (Box 9)
    Scope and Contents
    Reprint. From a 1991 event.
  - Biography, 2023 (Box 9)
  - Turning Points presentation script, 2022 (Box 9)
    Script from a presentation given by Earlene Craver Leijonhufvud at the University of Trento during a ceremony honoring Axel Leijonhufvud.
- Correspondence, 1963-1990s
  Includes correspondence from individuals such as Armen Alchian, Robert W. Clower, Robert Dorfman, Alan G. Gowman, Bert Hoselitz, Erik Lundberg, Gunnar Myrdal, and Joan Robinson. Some correspondence also includes published works sent to Leijonhufvud. Organized into two subseries: Professional Correspondents and Chronological Correspondence.
  Arrangement
  This series was compiled from multiple separate accessions and original folder titles have been retained. There may be material from single correspondents present in multiple folders.
  - Professional Correspondents, 1964-1990s
    - American Economic Review, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
    - American Scandinavian Foundation, 1971-1979 (Box 1)
    - William Baumol, 1990s (Box 9)
    - Canada Council research grant applications, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Duskin Publishing Company interview, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Robert V. Eagley, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Econometrica, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Economic Journal, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Santiago Fernandes, 1964-1973 (Box 1)
    - Herschel Grossman, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - J. Hirshleiffer, 1975 (Box 1)
    - History of Political Economy, 1971-1975, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Lynn Jensen, 1973 (Box 1)
    - Journal of Money, Credit, and Banking, 1968-1973 (Box 1)
    - Journal of Political Economy, 1969-1975 (Box 1)
    - Abba P. Lerner, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Fritz Machlup, 1972 (Box 1)
    - Allan H. Meltzer, 1967 (Box 1)
    - Allan Meltzer, 1980s-1990s (Box 10)
    - National Science Foundation, 1970-1974 (Box 1)
    - National Science Foundation, 1976-1980 (Box 1)
    - National Science Foundation grant proposal, 1987 (Box 11)
    - Jürg Niehans, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Note Economiche (Economic Notes), 1990s (Box 11)
    - Gerald P. O'Driscoll, 1970s-1990s (Box 11)
    - Professional, A-E (Box 1)
    - Professional, A-E, 1970s-1990s; 29 folders (Box 9)
    - Professional, F-L (Box 1)
    - Professional, F-Na, 1970s-1990s; 38 folders (Box 10)
    - Professional, M-R (Box 2)
    - Professional, Ne-Z, 1970s-1990s; 18 folders (Box 11)
    - Professional, S-Y (Box 2)
    - Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1973-1977 (Box 2)
    - Joan Robinson, 1966-1970 (Box 2)
    - Joan Robinson, 1977 (Box 11)
    - Anna Schwartz, 1980s (Box 11)
    - Martin Shubik, 1980s-1990s (Box 11)
    - Robert M. Solow, 1970s-1990s (Box 11)
    - Southern Economic Association, 1971 (Box 2)
    - Swedish Journal of Economics, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - Western Economic Journal, 1967-1971 (Box 2)
    - James G. Witte, 1966-1973 (Box 2)
    - Juan Urrutia, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1963-1983
    - Teaching positions, 1963-1964 (Box 2)
    - Dissertation, 1964 (Box 2)
    - Dissertation, 1966-1967 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1966-1969 (Box 2)
    - Misceallenous correspondence, A-L, 1970s (Box 9)
    - Misceallenous correspondence, M-Z, 1970s-1983 (Box 9)
    - Permissions for book publication, 1968 July (Box 2)
    - Permissions for book publication, 1968 Aug. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence during stay in Sweden, 1968 Dec.-1969 Sept. (Box 2)
    - Personal correspondence, 1969 Aug.-1970 Oct. (Box 2)
    - Students, 1969-1973 and undated (Box 2)
    - Teaching position feelers, 1972 (Box 2)
    - General memos, 1965-1973 (Box 2)
    - General memos, 1972-1974 (Box 2)
    - Comparisons, 1971-1975 (Box 2)
- Writings, Research, and Works, 1953-1980s
  Writings by Leijonhufvud and others (including his thesis and dissertation), teaching material, coursework, and research and notes. Organized into seven subseries: Writings; Events; Lecture Notes; Dissertation; Graduate Work; Research, Notes, and Sketches; and Writings by Others.
  - Writings, 1958-1980s and undated
    Drafts and completed manuscripts written by Leijonhufvud. Includes the beginnings of a book project with Robert W. Clower, The Coordination of Economic Activities. Arranged alphabetically.
    - An Approach to the Study of the Formal Organization of Producers' Interests, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Autonomous and Instrumental Organizations-The Question of Control, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Coalitions and the Aggregation Problems, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Commentary on the Phillips-Curve Debate, 1973 (Box 3)
    - Comments on Douglas Rimmer: Schumpeter and the Underdeveloped Countries, 1962 (Box 3)
    - The Concepts of Goal and Foundation in Administrative Theory, 1961 (Box 3)
    - The Coordination of Economic Activities, Book Project, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Effective Demand Failures, 1972 (Box 3)
    - Income and Employment Theory, undated (Box 3)
    - The Interdependence of Preference-Maps in the Duesenberry Theory of Consumer Behavior, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Investment Demand in Monetary Neoclassical Macroeconomic Models, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Investment Flows and the Rate of Interest: The Possibility of a 'Perverse' Mechanism, undated (Box 3)
    - Knight's Crusonia and the Question of Diminishing Returns to Investment, undated (Box 3)
    - Labor Service Transactions, undated (Box 3)
    - A Note on the Interest Elasticity of Investment, 1964-1965 (Box 3)
    - Notes on Lipsey's Theory of the Phillips Relation, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Notes on Physical Capital and the Metastatic Model, 1962 (Box 3)
    - Notes on the Rate of Interest in the Stationary State, 1963 (Box 3)
    - Notes on the Theory of Industrial Expansion, 1961-1963 (Box 3)
    - Notes on the Theory of Markets, undated (Box 3)
    - On Keynesian Economics and the Economics of Keynes, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Problems in the Theory of the Firm: The Profit-Maximizing Hypothesis, 1960 (Box 3)
    - The Rate of Investment in Indivisible Projects at Alternative Rates of Discount, 1962 (Box 3)
    - The Report of the Commission on Money and Credit: A Review, 1961 (Box 3)
    - The Theory of Industrial Expansion-A Look in Pandora's Box, 1963-1964 (Box 3)
    - Reviews, 1960s-1980s (Box 11)
    - Say's Principle, What it Means and Doesn't Mean: Parts I and II, undated (Box 3)
    - Schumpeter's Theory of Interest: The Controversy with Böhm-Bawerk, undated (Box 3)
    - Stereotypes and the Aggregation of Interests, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Writings in Swedish, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
  - Events, 1987-1989
    - Siena I, 1987 (Box 11)
    - Siena II, 1988 (Box 12)
    - Siena III, 1989 (Box 12)
    - Western Economic Association (Vancouver), 1987 July (Box 12)
  - Lecture Notes, 1966-1974 and undated
    Syllabi, exams, handouts, and notes, chiefly from undergraduate classes taught by Leijonhufvud at the University of California, Los Angeles. Also includes one folder of material from a class taught at the Economics Institute at the University of Colorado. Most folders contain notes from several semesters, and certain folders include student seating charts for certain semesters. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Economics 100B (Box 4)
    - Economics 102 (Box 4)
    - Economics 105: Introduction to Macrodynamics, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Economics 135: Money and Banking (Box 4)
    - Economics 195: Principles of International Trade (Box 4)
    - Economics 196 (Box 4)
    - Economics 197: International Finance (Box 4)
    - Economics 202A: Income, Employment, and Monetary Theory (Box 4)
    - Economics 202B: Income, Employment, and Monetary Theory (Box 4)
    - Economics 202C: Income, Employment, and Monetary Theory (Box 4)
    - Economics Institute: Macroeconomic Theory, 1972 (Box 4)
    - UCLA professorship paperwork (Box 4)
    - UCLA skits and cartoon, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 12)
  - Dissertation, 1964-1968 and undated
    Material related to Leijonhufvud's doctoral dissertation completed at Northwestern University in 1968. Includes two initial printings and two complete copies of the final printing. This would become his first published book, On Keynesian Economics and the Economics of Keynes: A Study in Monetary Theory (1968).
    - Early work (Box 4)
    - Proposal (Box 4)
    - Chapter 1 draft (Box 4)
    - Chapter 2 draft (Box 5)
    - Chapter 3 draft (Box 5)
    - Chapter 4 draft (Box 5)
    - Chapter 5 draft and postscript (Box 5)
    - Unused material (Box 5)
    - Notes, 4 folders (Box 5)
    - Final draft of dissertation, First copy (Box 5)
    - Final draft of dissertation, Second copy (Box 6)
    - Annotated dissertation: Volume I (Box 6)
    - Completed dissertation: Volume I, 2 volumes (Box 6)
    - Completed dissertation: Volume II, 1 volume (Box 6)
    - Completed dissertation: Volume II, 1 volume (Box 7)
  - Graduate Work, 1960-1961
    Material from Leijonhufvud's graduate studies at the University of Pittsburgh. Includes four bound volumes with notes, writings, and handouts.
    - Proposal for Masters thesis, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Masters thesis draft, 1961, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Masters thesis manuscript, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Graduate papers, 1960-1961 (Box 7)
    - Bound volumes of Leijonhufvud's graduate studies notes and papers, 4 volumes (Box 7)
  - Research, Notes, and Sketches, 1964-1980s and undated
    Research material used in Leijonhufvud's writings, such as "Commentary on the Phillips-Curve Debate," and other notes.
    - Phillips Curves (Box 8)
    - Rent Control (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous notes, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 12)
    - Ph.D. notes (Box 8)
    - Inflation cases, 1980s (Box 12)
    - Inflation and stagflation, 1980s (Box 12)
    - Policy, 1970s-1980s (Box 12)
    - Sketches of economists, 1980s (Box 12)
      Portraits of economists, sketched by Leijonhufvud. Leijonhufvud likely created these sketches at conferences and other events.
  - Writings by Others, 1953-1977 and undated
    Writings sent to Leijonhufvud by his colleagues. The issue of Business Week includes an article on Keynesian economists, including Leijonhufvud. Econoblast is a monthly publication by the graduate students of Northwestern University. Writings from Joan Robinson include both published and unpublished manuscripts. Arranged alphabetically.
    - Business Week, 1975 May 12 (Box 8)
    - Robert W. Clower, The Keynesian Paradigm: An Attempt at Reconstruction, 1971 (Box 8)
    - Econoblast, 1965 Dec. (Box 8)
    - Peter W. Howitt, Studies in the Theory of Monetary Dynamics, 1973 (Box 8)
    - Writings by Lars Jonung, 1970s-1980s; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Thomas Mayer, The Interest Rate Snap-Back and its Implication for the Keynesian Quantity Theory Dispute, 1974 (Box 8)
    - Bertil Ohlin, 1933 and 1977-Some Expansion Policy Problems in Cases of Unbalanced Domestic and International Economic Relations, 1977 (Box 8)
    - Joan Robinson, On Re-Reading Marx, 1953 (Box 8)
    - Joan Robinson, other writings (Box 8)
    - Thomas R. Saving, Outside Money, Inside Money, and the Real Balance Effect, undated (Box 8)
    - Unidentified author, The Aggregative Structure of Keynes' General Theory, undated (Box 8)